I've spent the last decade
لقد قضيت العقد الماضي
subjecting myself to pain and humiliation,
معرضاً نفسي للألم و الإذلال
hopefully for a good cause,
من أجل قضية سامية كما اّمل
which is self-improvement.
والتي هي تحسين الذات
And I've done this in three parts.
وكنت أقوم بذلك على ثلاثة مراحل
So first I started with the mind.
لقد بدأت اولا فيما يخص الفكر
And I decided to try to get smarter
فقررت أن أصبح أكثر ذكاءاً
by reading the entire Encyclopedia Britannica
عن طريق قراءة الموسوعة البريطانية بأكلمها
from A to Z --
من الألف إلى الياء
or, more precisely, from "a-ak" to "Zywiec."
من بدقة اكثر من الاختصار " إيه - إيه كي " الى كلمة " زيفيتش "
And here's a little image of that.
وهذه صورة عن هذا
And this was an amazing year.
وقد كانت تلك سنة مميزة
It was really a fascinating journey.
لقد كانت فعلاً رحلة ممتعة
It was painful at times,
وقد كانت مؤلمة في بعض الاحيان
especially for those around me.
خاصة لمن هم من حولي
My wife started to fine me one dollar
فقد فرضت زوجي علي غرامة قدرها دولاراً واحداً
for every irrelevant fact I inserted into conversation.
لكل معلومة غير متصلة أدخلها في حواراتنا
So it had its downsides.
إذا فـ للأمر سلبياته
But after that,
ولكن بعد هذا
I decided to work on the spirit.
قررت ان انتقل الى الروح
As I mentioned last year,
كما ذكرت السنة الماضية
I grew up with no religion at all.
كنت أعيش دون أي إعتقاد ديني / روحاني
I'm Jewish,
انا يهودي في الاساس
but I'm Jewish in the same way the Olive Garden is Italian.
ولكني يهودي بقدر ما هو أوليف جاردن إيطالي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Not really.
ليس حقاً
But I decided to learn about the Bible and my heritage
ولكني قررت أن ادرس الانجيل و تراثي
by actually diving in
عن طريق الغوص فيه
and trying to live it and immerse myself in it.
ومحاولة العيش تبعاُ له و زج نفسي في طياته
So I decided to follow all the rules of the Bible.
لذا قررت ان امضي خلف قواعد الانجيل وان اتبعها جميعها
And from the Ten Commandments
من الوصايا العشر
to growing my beard --
حتى خبز خبزي
because Leviticus says you cannot shave.
ولأن " لاويين " قال يجب أن لا نحلق شعرنا
So this is what I looked like by the end.
هذا ما بدوت عليه في آخر المطاف
Thank you for that reaction.
شكراً على ردة فعلكم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I look a little like Moses, or Ted Kaczynski.
لقد بدوت كموسى ربما , أو تيد كازنينسكي
I got both of them.
أو ربما كلاهما
So there was the topiary there.
كان هناك العصى كما في الصورة ..
And there's the sheep.
وهاهو الحمل
Now the final part of the trilogy
اما المرحلة الثالثة
was I wanted to focus on the body
فقد أردت أن أركز على جسدي
and try to be the healthiest person I could be,
وحاولت أن اكون الاكثر صحة على قدر ما استطيع
the healthiest person alive.
الشخص الاكثر صحة على وجه الارض
So that's what I've been doing the last couple of years.
وهذا ما كنت اقوم على مدى السنتين السابقتين
And I just finished a couple of months ago.
وقد انتهيت من ذلك في الشهرين الماضيين
And I have to say, thank God.
وعلي أن أقول , الحمد لله
Because living so healthily was killing me.
لان العيش " بصحة كبيرة " كاد يقتلني
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It was so overwhelming,
لقد كان الامر مرهقاً جداً
because the amount of things you have to do,
بسبب الكمية من الامور التي يتوجب عليك القيام بها
it's just mind-boggling.
انها امرٌ متعب فكرياً جداً
I was listening to all the experts
كنت استمع لكل الخبراء
and talking to sort of a board of medical advisers.
واتحدث لما يمكن تسميته مجلس صحة استشاري
And they were telling me
وكانوا يوجهونني نحو
all the things I had to do.
كل الامور التي يتجوب علي القيام بها
I had to eat right,
كان يتوجب علي الاكل بصورة صحيحة
exercise, meditate, pet dogs,
و التدريب , و التامل , و رعاية الكلاب
because that lowers the blood pressure.
لان ذلك يخفض من ضغط الدم
I wrote the book on a treadmill,
وقد كتبت كتاباً و أنا اسير على ممشى رياضي
and it took me about a thousand miles
وقد تطلب ذلك مني 1000 ميل
to write the book.
من اجل كتابة الكتاب
I had to put on sunscreen.
لقد وضعت مرهم الوقاية من الشمس
This was no small feat,
لم يكن هناك اي تسامح فيما يخص ذلك
because if you listen to dermatologists,
لان علماء البشرة ان استمعت لهم يقولون
they say that you should have a shot glass full of sunscreen.
انه يجب ان نستخدم ما يعادل كأس الفودكا من مرهم وقاية البشرة
And you have to reapply it every two to four hours.
ويجب ان نجدد ذلك كل اربع ساعات
So I think half of my book advance
لذا اعتقد ان نصف كتابي
went into sunscreen.
يخص مرهم الوقاية من الشمس
I was like a glazed doughnut
لقد بدوت كرجل " مقزز " لامع
for most of the year.
لاكثر من عام
There was the washing of hands.
وكان يتوجب علي غسل يديَ
I had to do that properly.
وكان يتوجب القيام بذلك بصورة صحيحة
And my immunologist told me
وقال لي مسؤول جهازي المناعي
that I should also wipe down
انه يتوجب علي التخلص من
all of the remote controls and iPhones in my house,
كل الاجهزة الالكترونية مثل اجهزة التحكم والاي فون في منزلي
because those are just orgies of germs.
لانها موطن للجراثيم
So that took a lot of time.
وقد تطلب ذلك وقتا طويلاً
I also tried to be the safest person I could be,
وقد حاولت ان اكون الشخص الاكثر حرصاً على الامان بقدر الامكان
because that's a part of health.
لان ذلك جزء من الصحة و السلامة
I was inspired
وقد ألهمني
by the Danish Safety Council.
مجلس السلامة الهولندي
They started a public campaign
فقد بدأوا بحملة شعبية
that says, "A walking helmet is a good helmet."
تنص على ( خوذة المشي .. خوذة حسنة )
So they believe you should not just wear helmets for biking,
فهم يؤمنون ان الخوذات ليس فحسب لركوب الدراجات الهوائية
but also for walking around.
بل للمشي أيضاً
And you can see there
ويمكنكم ان ترون هنا
they're shopping with their helmets.
كيف انهم يتسوقون بخوذهم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Well yeah, I tried that.
حسناً .. لقد جربت هذا
Now it's a little extreme, I admit.
اعترف ان هذا مبالغ فيه و متطرف
But if you think about this,
ولكن ان فكرتم حيال هذا
this is actually -- the "Freakonomics" authors wrote about this --
وهذا حقاً ما كتبه بعض الكتاب الاقتصاديون المهووسون
that more people die on a per mile basis
ان هناك اشخاص يموتون تبعاً لقياس الاميال - اميال السير -
from drunk walking
بسبب المشي بحالة سكر
than from drunk driving.
أكثر من الناس التي تموت تبعاً للقيادة بحالة سكر
So something to think about tonight
وهو شيء يجب ان تفكروا فيه الليلة
if you've had a couple.
ان شربتم كأسين
So I finished,
وها قد انتهيت
and it was a success in a sense.
وكان هذا نجاحاً من حيث المبدأ
All of the markers went in the right direction.
فكل مؤشراتي توجهت نحو مجالها الصحيح
My cholesterol went down, I lost weight,
فانخفض الكوليسترول لدي . وفقدت الوزن الزائد
my wife stopped telling me that I looked pregnant.
وتوقفت زوجتي عن القول لي أنني أبدو كإمرأة حامل
So that was nice.
وكان هذا جميلاً
And it was successful overall.
وكان نجاحاً على جميع الاصعدة
But I also learned that I was too healthy,
ولكني تعلمت ايضاً انني كنت " صحياً "
and that was unhealthy.
اكثر مما يجب وهذا بحد ذاته ليس صحياً
I was so focused on doing all these things
لقد كنت اهتم كثيراً بكل تلك الامور
that I was neglecting my friends and family.
لدرجة انني كنت اهمل اصدقائي وافراد عائلتي
And as Dan Buettner can tell you,
وكما يمكن أن يخبرنا " دان بوتنر "
having a strong social network
ان الحصول على شبكة اجتماعية قوية
is so crucial to our health.
هو امرٌ حساس و ضروري لصحتنا
So I finished.
لذا لقد انهيتي مهمتي
And I kind of went overboard
و من ثم فقدت جماحي
on the week after the project was over.
بعد ان انتهى المشروع باسبوع
I went to the dark side,
فانتقلت الى الجانب المظلم
and I just indulged myself.
وقد اهملت نفسي تماما
It was like something out of Caligula.
كان الامر كما الخارج من كالايجولا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Without the sex part.
بدون الاستغناء عن الجنس ..
Because I have three young kids,
لانه لدي ثلاثة اطفال
so that wasn't happening.
وهذا ما حدث
But the over-eating and over-drinking, definitely.
لقد اكلت بشراهة و سكرت بإفراط
And I finally have stabilized.
وفي النهاية استقريت
So now I'm back
وقد عدت الآن
to adopting many -- not all; I don't wear a helmet anymore --
إلى التأقلم .. لم اعد لكل شيء .. فلم اعد ارتدي الخوذة
but dozens of healthy behaviors
ولكن استعدت ديزينتين من التصرفات الصحية
that I adopted during my year.
التي كنت اقوم بها في تلك السنة
It was really a life-changing project.
لقد كان فعلاً مشروعاً غير حياتي
And I, of course, don't have time to go into all of them.
وحتما ليس لدي الوقت الكافي لكي اشرح لكم كل شيء
Let me just tell you two really quickly.
ولكن سوف اخبركم بأمرين بسرعة
The first is -- and this was surprising to me;
الاول و قد كان مفاجئاً بالنسبة لي :
I didn't expect this to come out --
ولم اكن اتوقعه على الاطلاق
but I live a much quieter life now.
أنا الآن اعيش حياة أكثر هدوءاً
Because we live in such a noisy world.
لاننا نعيش في عالم ضوضائي جداً
There's trains and planes and cars
فهناك الطائرات و السيارات و القطارات
and Bill O'Reilly, he's very noisy.
و هناك " بيل أوريلي " .. وهو مزعج حقاً
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And this is a real underestimated, under-appreciated health hazard --
وهذه مشكة صحية يتم التقليل من شأنها و إهمالها
not just because it harms our hearing, which it obviously does,
ليس بسبب انها تؤذي سمعنا فحسب - وهي كذلك فعلاً -
but it actually initiates
ولكن - الضوضاء - تؤذي
the fight-or-flight response.
ردات الفعل بخصوص ( الاقتتال \ الهرب )
A loud noise will get your fight-or-flight response going.
فالضوضاء العادية تذهب ردات الفعل بخصوص ( الاقتتال \ الهرب )
And this, over the years,
وعلى مدى سنوات
can cause real damage, cardiovascular damage.
قد يسبب ذلك اعطاباً في الاوعية الدموية والقلب
The World Health Organization just did a big study
لقد قامت منظمة الصحة العالمية بدراسة كبيرة
that they published this year.
قد تم نشرها هذا العالم
And it was done in Europe.
وقد تمت في أوروبا
And they estimated
وهي تقدر
that 1.6 million years of healthy living
ان 1.6 مليون سنة من العيش الصحي
are lost every year in Europe
تخسرها أوروبا كل عام
because of noise pollution.
بسبب التلوث الضوضائي
So they think it's actually very deadly.
فهم يرون الضوضاء مميتة حقاً
And by the way,
وبالمناسبة
it's also terrible for your brain.
هي مؤذية أيضاً لدماغك
It really impairs cognition.
و هذا يضعف الإدراك حقاً
And our Founding Fathers knew about this.
وقد علم أسلافنا ذلك
When they wrote the Constitution,
عندما كتبوا دستور البلاد
they put dirt all over the cobblestones outside the hall
فقاموا وضع طين حول كل البحص الذي يحيط القاعة
so that they could concentrate.
من اجل ان يحافظوا على تركيزهم ..
So without noise reduction technology,
فمن غير تكنولوجيا امتصاص الضوضاء ما كانت
our country would not exist.
دولتنا موجودة
So as a patriot,
وكشخص وطني
I felt it was important to --
شعرت انه من الضروري
I wear all the earplugs and the earphones,
ان أردتي سماعات الاذنين و واقيات السمع
and it's really improved my life
وقد حسن ذلك حياتي الشخصية
in a surprising and unexpected way.
بصورة مفاجئة لم اكن اتوقعها على الاطلاق
And the second point I want to make, the final point,
و النقطة الثانية التي اريد ان اتحدث عنها و هي الاخيرة
is that -- and it's actually been a theme of TEDMED --
و قد كانت شعاراً لأحد مؤتمرات تيد الطبية
that joy is so important to your health,
هي ان الفرح و السعادة امرٌ مهم جداً لصحتك
that very few of these behaviors
وهذه التصرفات القليلة
will stick with me
سوف استمر بها
unless there's some sense of pleasure and joy in them.
الا لو لم تكن تحوي احساساً بالمتعة في طياتها
And just to give you one instance of this:
ولأعطيكم مثالاً عن هذا
food.
الطعام
The junk food industry
صناعة الاطعمة السريعة
is really great
هي فعلاً صناعة مميزة
at pressing our pleasure buttons
في تحفيز مناطق المتعة لدينا
and figuring out what's the most pleasurable.
واكتشاف ما هو اكثر متعة
But I think we can use their techniques
وانا اعتقد انه بالامكان استخدام تقنياتهم
and apply them to healthy food.
وتطبيقها على الطعام الصحي
To give just one example,
ولاعطيكم مثالا واحد على ذلك
we love crunchiness, mouthfeel.
جميعنا يحب القرمشة التي نشعر بها في أفواهنا
So I basically have tried to incorporate crunchiness
وما حاولت القيام به هو اضفاء القرمشة
into a lot of my recipes --
على الكثير من وصفاتي
throw in some sunflower seeds.
وخاصة تلك التي تتضمن بذور عباد الشمس
And you can almost trick yourself
فيمكنك ان تخدع نفسك
into thinking you're eating Doritos.
فتظن نفسك تأكل ما يشابه " الدوريتوس "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And it has made me a healthier person.
وقد ساعد ذلك في ان اصبح اكثر صحة
So that is it.
هذا ما اريد قوله
The book about it comes out in April.
الكتاب الذي سوف اطلقه في شهر أبريل
It's called "Drop Dead Healthy."
يدعى " السقوط ميتا من الصحة "
And I hope that I don't get sick during the book tour.
واتمنى ان لا أصاب بالاعياء اثناء كتابته
That's my greatest hope.
فهذا أملي الكبير
So thank you very much.
وشكراً لكم جزيلاً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)